City Club of Albany; Records apap082
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
City Club of Albany Records
1945-1961
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
City Club of Albany
apap082
0.3 cubic ft.
The collection documents the City Club of Albany and primarily contains organizational records from 1957-1959, mainly concerned with issues of the Citizen's Platform. The collection is composed chiefly of files retained by Harriet D. Adams as vice president of the club when it was particularly interested in urban planning.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group, excpet for the poster, were donated to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in the 1980s.
Lisa Gray donated the poster 2005 June.
Biographical History
The City Club of Albany was established February 5, 1919, to give "women an opportunity through membership to take an intelligent part in public affairs."[1] The group participated in public affairs with "a program that determines through careful study and full discussion what [its] aims should be, and helps achieve those aims by informing and stimulating public opinion."[2] The City Club was interested in a variety of issues including services for senior citizens, city planning, world health, youth, environmental concerns, and others. The Club shared information in the form of pamphlets and brochures often produced by other organizations. The Club held regular meetings as well as annual anniversary luncheons and events.
1. Elizabeth M. Smith, "The City Club States its Credo," 1.2. The City Club of Albany, New York, "Handbook, 1947-1948," 3.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the City Club of Albany and contains organizational records from 1957-1959 mainly concerned with issues of the Citizen's Platform. The collection is composed chiefly of files retained by Harriet D. Adams as vice president of the club when it was particularly interested in urban planning. The Citizen's Platform of 1957 consisted of the City Club's position on issues such as city planning, housing, health, education, child welfare, recreation, safety and law enforcement, local government finances, and "a cleaner Albany." City Planning materials from Schenectady, New York were also retained as background material. Organizational records also include the City Club's mission, membership, monthly reports, a budget report, reports from the Nominating Committee and the Civic Affairs Committee, newsletters, and correspondence of the Civic Affairs Committee. Other materials include summary reports, notes, news clippings primarily related to city planning and housing, 1957-1959, and materials relating to the City Club of Albany's 40th anniversary in 1959. The publications folder includes materials produced by other organizations such as the Junior League, United Nations, New York City Youth Board, and the New York State Youth Commission on topics covering world health, youth, and human rights.
The poster by Jerry Costello honors Mrs. Arthur W. Wright, president of the City Club of Albany and Costello's aunt. The poster includes a drawing of Mrs. Wright and references to the Armed Forces Day parade ("today"), "Tidy Up for Tulip Time," and 5th Annual Albany Scholastic Track and Field Championships.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Women--New York (State)--Societies and clubs; City planning--New York (State)--Albany; Albany (N.Y.)--Societies and clubs; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuals; Newsletters; Adams, Harriet Dyer; City Club of Albany (Albany, N.Y.)
- City Club, 40th Anniversary Luncheon and Tea, 1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 1)
- City Club, Committee Reports and Budgets, 1958-1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 2)
- City Club, Correspondence to Civic Affairs Committee, 1958 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 3)
- City Club, Membership, Mission, Citizen's Platform, 1945; 1947-1950; 1957-1961 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 4)
- City Club, Newsletters, 1958-1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 5)
- City Planning, Albany Master Plan and American Council to Improve Our Neighborhoods (ACTION), 1958 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 6)
- Council of Community Services of the Albany Area, Annual Report and Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 7)
- Finances, City and County, News Clippings and Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 8)
- Nature Conservancy, News Clippings and Notes, 1958 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 9)
- News Clippings, 1957-1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 10)
- Poster, Honoring Mrs. Arthur W. Wright, by Jerry Costello, ca. 1953 (Flat-file 1)
- Publications, 1957-1959 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 11)
- Senior Citizens, Brochures, 1949; 1957; Undated (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 12)
- Tivoli Lakes Nature Study Sanctuary, 1958 (Box 1 (City Club of Albany Records), Folder 13)